In 1972,
the first Landsat satellite
was launched into orbit,
ushering in a revolutionary
new era of earth observation.
More than 50 years
and eight satellites later,
the Landsat program
has collected
an immense amount of data
that's proven
an invaluable resource
to scientists
studying the complexities
of our planet's surface.
The abundance of data
provides insights,
but it can also pose
a daunting challenge
for researchers to extract
and analyze information.
Landsat 8 and 9 alone each gather
close to a terabyte of data per day.
Enter Artificial Intelligence.
AI's popularity has taken off
in recent years
with new tools
that allow users to generate
imagery, transcribe audio,
and even compose music
at the click of a button.
This is nothing new
for the scientific community,
however, which have been using
artificial intelligence
methods for decades.
When it comes
to working with Landsat data,
one of the most popular A.I.
tools is machine learning.
Machine learning is a subset of AI
that can train
computer programs
to recognize patterns
and analyze imagery, skills
that prove
exceptionally useful
in the application of Landsat data.
In fact, when combined with Landsat
machine learning models have led
to a number of advances across a variety
of scientific fields,
granting further insight
into our planet's
past, present and future.
One of the major challenges
of working
with satellite imagery
like Landsat can actually be
found up in the sky,
clouds
obscuring Earth's surface
and casting
shadows
that reduce visibility.
A cloudy day
can be a downright nuisance
when it comes to analyzing
certain satellite imagery.
Pinpointing these clouds
helps to improve data quality
by removing
noise and artifacts,
making it easier
to detect changes over time.
But while
accurate cloud detection
across a massive dataset
such as Landsat
would be a tall
task for any one
human, it's a piece of cake
for a computer.
In 2019, researchers
from Oregon State University
constructed
a deep convolutional
neural network model
a machine learning tool
that excels
at recognizing patterns
in imagery.
With the help of existing
Landsat 8 data,
they taught their neural network
to automatically detect clouds
in satellite imagery
with an amazing 97.1%
accuracy rate.
The researchers
believe in the future
cloud detection algorithms
like this one
could even be harnessed
to identify clouds across the
entire Landsat 8 archive.
Machine learning's
benefits don't just end
when the clouds
clear - down on the ground
there's plenty
to keep an eye on.
Our planet's one
constant is change.
Earth's surface
is perpetually evolving due
to human and natural forces.
Landsat its ability
to track these changes over
time has proven
to be an incredible asset
to the scientific community,
especially when used in
concert with machine learning.
For example, researchers
from the University of Texas
at Austin used Landsat data
with a random force
classifier, yet
another type of machine
learning tool that combines
multiple decision trees
to make predictions.
Using data from Landsats 4
through 8,
They used the classifier
to map changes in land use
in northwestern Belize
from the 1980s to the present.
The results showed that
tropical forests and wetlands
that don't have
a designated protection status
are increasingly vulnerable
to deforestation due
to Belize's expanding
industrial agriculture.
By combining
these new advances in machine
learning with Landsat
to capacity
for looking back in time,
researchers
believe in the future,
this approach would make it
possible
to provide robust estimates
of deforestation in Belize.
As climate change drives our
planet's temperatures higher,
so does the
prevalence of extreme events
that put ecosystems at risk.
Wildfires across
the globe have increased
in frequency and intensity.
Australia is no stranger
to these types of fires.
The 2019-2020 bushfire season
was one of the most
destructive on record.
Using satellite imagery
to pinpoint
when and where
wildfires are burning
could be an important tool
for assessing damage
in future fires.
Researchers
at the University of Western
Australia
have developed a new machine
learning approach with
the help of Landsat 8 data
to generate a 16-year
history of wildfire severity
in the eucalyptus forests
of the continent's southwest.
They fed data gathered by
satellites, including Landsat 8
from 2005 to 2020
into a supervised classifier
a type of machine
learning algorithm
that learns to classify
data based on labeled examples
provided during training.
By teaching the algorithm
with examples from the past.
This method of machine
learning could be used
to predict the severity
of future wildfires.
Critical data
that could aid in the
management and conservation
of Australia's
extensive eucalyptus forests.
These are just a few examples
of the remarkable ways
Landsat data and machine
learning tools are unlocking
new possibilities
for understanding our planet.
This combination
has already led
to significant advances
in agriculture,
forestry,
urban planning, climate change
research and more
as more satellite data
becomes available and machine
learning techniques
continue to improve.
So too will the potential
for applications
in additional fields
critical to the health
of our planet's ecosystems.
In tackling
the complex challenges
of today and tomorrow,
the blending of Landsat data
and machine
learning will be vital to help
people
make better decisions
to protect our planet.
In 1972, the
Landsat mission launched its
first satellite into orbit,
ushering in a revolutionary
new era of earth
observation.
The Landsat mission
has collected
an immense amount of data
that's proven
an invaluable resource
to scientists
studying the complexities
of our planet's surface.
The incredible abundance
of data provides insights,
but it can also pose
a daunting challenge
for researchers to extract
and analyze information.
Landsat eight and nine alone,
each gather
close to a terabyte of data
per day.
Enter artificial intelligence
with new tools
that allow users to generate
imagery, transcribe audio,
and even compose music
at the click of a button.
This is nothing new
for the scientific community,
however, which have been using
artificial intelligence
methods for decades.
When it comes to working
with Landsat data.
One of the most popular A.I.
tools is machine learning.
Machine
learning is a subset of A.I.
that can train
computer programs
to recognize patterns
and analyze imagery skills
that prove exceptional useful
in the application of Landsat
data.
In fact,
when combined with Landsat
machine learning models
have led to a number
of advances across a variety
of scientific fields,
granting further insight
into our planet's past,
present and future.
One of the major challenges
of working
with satellite imagery
like Landsat
can actually be
found up in the sky, clouds
obscuring the Earth's surface
and casting
shadows
that reduce visibility.
A cloudy day
can be a downright nuisance
when it comes to analyzing
certain satellite imagery.
Accurately detecting these
pesky clouds would be a tall
task for any one human,
but a piece of cake
for a computer.
In 2019, researchers
from Oregon State University
constructed
a deep convolutional neural
network model
a machine learning tool
that excels at recognizing
patterns in imagery.
With the help of existing
Landsat eight data,
they taught
their neural network
to automatically detect clouds
and satellite imagery
with an amazing 97.1%
accuracy rate.
The researchers
believe in the future,
this machine learning
technique
could even be harnessed
to identify clouds
across the entire Landsat
eight archive.
Machine learning benefits
don't just end when the clouds
clear down on the ground.
There's plenty
to keep an eye on.
Our planet's one
constant is change.
Earth's surface
is perpetually evolving due
to human and natural forces.
Landsat its ability to track
these changes over time
has proven to be
an incredible asset
to the scientific community,
especially when used in
concert with machine learning.
For example, researchers
from the University of Texas
at Austin
used the Landsat data
with a random forest
classifier,
yet another type of machine
learning tool that combines
multiple decision trees
to make predictions.
Using data from Landsat four
through eight.
They used the classifier
to map the changes in land use
in northwestern Belize
from the 1980s to the present.
The results showed that
tropical forests and wetlands
don't have
a designated protection status
or are increasingly vulnerable
to deforestation
due to Belize's expanding
industrial agriculture.
By combining
these new advances in machine
learning with Landsat
to capacity
for looking back in time,
researchers
believe this approach
makes it possible
to provide robust estimates
of deforestation in Belize.
Going forward,
as climate change drives
our planet's temperatures
higher,
so does the prevalence
of extreme events
that put ecosystems at risk.
Wildfires across
the globe has seen an increase
in frequency and intensity.
Australia is no stranger
to these types of fires.
The 2019
2020 bushfire season
was one of the most
destructive on record.
Using satellite imagery
to pinpoint
when and where
wildfires are burning
can be an important tool
for assessing damage
and preventing future fires.
Researchers at the University
of Western Australia
to generate a 16 year
history of wildfire severity
in the eucalyptus forests
of the continent's southwest.
They said data gathered by
satellites, including Landsat
eight from 2005 to 2020
into a supervised classifier,
a type of machine
learning algorithm
that learns to classify
data based on labeled examples
provided during training
by teaching the algorithm
with examples from the past.
This method of machine
learning could be used
to predict the severity
of future wildfires.
Critical data
that could aid in
the management
and conservation
of Australia's
extensive eucalyptus forests.
These were just a few examples
of the remarkable ways
the fusion of Landsat data
with machine learning tools
are unlocking
new possibilities
for understanding our planet.
This collaboration
has already led
to significant advances
in agriculture, forestry,
urban planning, climate change
research and more
as satellite data
such as Landsat becomes
increasingly available
and machine
learning techniques
continue to improve.
So too will
the potential for applications
in additional fields
critical to the health
of our planet's ecosystems.
In tackling
the complex challenges
of today and tomorrow,
the partnership
between Landsat data
and machine
learning will be vital to help
people make better decisions
to protect our planet.